<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The third part of The amours of Messalina wherein the secret intrigues of the four last years reign are compleated, and the love adventures of Polydorus King of the Gauls, and the late Queen of Albion, made publick / by a woman of quality ...</title>
            <author>Woman of quality, fl. 1689-1690.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64511</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T912</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14248</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">19135438</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 19135438</idno>
            <idno type="VID">108547</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64511)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 108547)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 478:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The third part of The amours of Messalina wherein the secret intrigues of the four last years reign are compleated, and the love adventures of Polydorus King of the Gauls, and the late Queen of Albion, made publick / by a woman of quality ...</title>
                  <author>Woman of quality, fl. 1689-1690.</author>
                  <author>Leti, Gregorio, 1630-1701.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>33 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Lyford,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Sometimes attributed to Gregorio Leti. Cf. NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>A libel on Mary of Modena, Queen consort of James II. Cf. NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mary, --  of Modena, Queen, consort of James II, King of England, 1658-1718.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  1660-1714.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:108547:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:108547:1"/>
            <p>THE <hi rend="blackletterType">Third Part</hi> OF THE AMOURS OF
Meſſalina. WHEREIN, The Secret Intrigues of the Four laſt Years Reign are
Compleated. AND THE Love Adventures of <hi>Polydorus</hi> King of the
<hi>Gauls,</hi> AND THE Late Queen of <hi>ALBION,</hi> Made Publick.</p>
            <p>By a Woman of Quality, a late Confidant of Q.
<hi>MESSALINA.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>John Lyford,</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="bookseller_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:108547:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:108547:2"/>
            <head>THE Bookſeller TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THE Promis'd, and long Expected <hi>Third Part of the Amours of
our</hi> MESSALINA, is here at your Service: And though ſome Criticks I am
inform'd (and indeed my <hi>Sale</hi> tells me as much) have not put an equal
value on the two foregoing <hi>Parts,</hi> the <hi>Second</hi> lying under the
Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute of much Inferiour to the <hi>Firſt:</hi> My <hi>Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi>
makes no other Apology, than that the Fair <hi>Meſſalina</hi> had ſo many
Engines at Work, in turning that great Hinge of the <hi>Pagan Glory,</hi> Her
<hi>Warming-pan Plot;</hi> and her Hands and Head ſo full of
<hi>Politicks</hi> on that Important Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, that She then wanted
Leiſure for <hi>Intrigue</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:108547:3"/>and <hi>Amour;</hi> which indeed
being the main De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light of the Generality of my Readers, might per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps
leſſen the Satisfaction expected from the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Part.</hi> But
ſince her Majeſties Departure from the <hi>Heretick Albion,</hi> has
Tranſlated her to a more agreeable and natural Element, the <hi>Pagan
Court</hi> of <hi>Gothland;</hi> her heavier and ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len
<hi>Buſineſs</hi> ſhe begins to ſhake off, and reſumes the lighter
Air of <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Pleaſure.</hi> And accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly we dare, without
Vanity, aſſure our <hi>Kind Reader,</hi> That the former Defects are
ſupplyed in the Entertainment of this <hi>Third Part</hi> of her Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory.
An Amorous <hi>Polydorus,</hi> little leſs famed under the Banners of
<hi>Cupid,</hi> than the ſometimes Glorious <hi>Britomard</hi> himſelf,
lying at the Feet of the Adored <hi>Meſſalina,</hi> affords a little mre
Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Adventure and Diverſion. With this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendation to our little
Volumn of the Great <hi>Meſſalina,</hi> We beg your preſent generous
Accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. And if you find your <hi>Meſſalina</hi> warm with any
extraordinary Spark for the Imperial <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lydorus;</hi> you are to
conſider, that the Sanctuary and Glorious Reception ſhe meets in the Court
of her ever firm Friend, the King of the <hi>Gauls,</hi> have Inſpired her
with no ſmall Gratitude to that MOST PAGAN <hi>Heroe,</hi> and
<hi>Champion</hi> of her <hi>Altars.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:108547:3"/>
            <head>The Third PART.</head>
            <p>LOVE could no longer brook this inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering Buſineſs in the
Court of <hi>Albion;</hi> for ſeeing with Indignation, how Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion daily
had intrench'd on his Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative, he reaſſumes his long neglected Darts,
and vows ſevere Revenge on his Rebellious Subjects. And now
<hi>Meſſalina</hi>'s haughty Heart, which vaſt aſpiring Hopes had long
engaged, ſoftens again in Gentleneſs and Love: She had ſeen the Languets
of her Charming Count, and heard his gentle Murmurs with Compaſſion; ſhe
knew the great reſtraint he forc'd upon his Heart, when by reaſon of her
numerous Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants, and Viſitours, he had not opportunity to breath his
Love; ſometimes a Wink, an Amorous Look, or Sigh, ſhe would by ſtealth
return; or otherwiſe, in ſome Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biguous Words, ſhe would diſcover her
Concern and Care, for his endearing Paſſion; but in ſuch dumb ſhows
alone, as there were more than Three Weeks ſpent, e're ſhe could
poſſibly engage, or ſpeak with him alone. Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring which time, her Beauty,
with the Satisfaction of her Mind, was much improved; and that forc'd
Abſtinence, which her pretended Child-bearing had made her under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go, conduc'd
as well to carry on the Cheat, as to revive ſome fading Glories in her Face,
caus'd by the Fears and Apprehenſions of Miſcarrying. Now, in Triumphant
Wiſe, ſhe'd Walk, and Look, and with Diſdainful Jeſts,<pb n="6" facs="tcp:108547:4"/>among her Confidents, Laugh at the weak dull <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> of
the Court. <hi>Come Dear</hi> Aſpaſia, would ſhe ſay, <hi>let us no
longer doubt of good Succeſs; let's every Year bring forth a Son, and ſtock
the Kingdom with a Race of</hi> Pagan <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; ſhall my aſpiring lofty
Soul, ſtoop to the nice Deſtructive Rules of their inſipid Morals? One
flight of</hi> Pagan <hi>Fancy quite out-ſtrips their heavy tedious Motions;
and till now, our Fears alone have been our Bugbear Apparitions: With how much
eaſe, did we Contrive and Finiſh, what ſome faint puny hearted Creatures
thought impoſſible? Oh how I am pleaſed to think how naturally I manag'd
the Intreague: Didſt thou obſerve, how gravely ſome would ſland; and
when my feigned Groans and Cries, would reach their Ears, how then Officiously
they'd ſhake their Heads, devoutly lifting up their Hands, and pray for my
Delivery? Then, when my ſeeming Pains would make me faintiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>, with what Concern they'd Sigh and
Whiſper, while I would gently graſp, and turn to thee, and ſmile at the
Succeſs of our Invention. Come, Come, let's ſee this Darling of our Hopes,
this Ground-work of our Everlaſting Joy; long Live, and Live to Reign, my
little blooming Life, and Live to be the Scourge of our Curſt</hi>
Chriſtian <hi>Foes; I'll ſwear thee, like another</hi> Hambal, <hi>their
Mortal Foe; each drop of Milk thou ſuck'ſt, ſhall breed an Age of Malice
in thy Heart; A</hi> Chriſtian's <hi>Name ſhall grate upon thy Soul, and
thou ſhalt prove the Plague of their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion; I'll breath my Spirit
through thy tender Pores, and make thy hatred of them Everlaſting; Down, down
ye</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans, <hi>to your Great Deliverer; Adore your Mighty Prince, and
your Redeemer: See how the baſe dejected</hi> Chriſtians <hi>ſhrink;
ſee how they Tremble at his Awful Frown:</hi> Albion <hi>is once again
Redeemed,</hi> Aſpaſia, <hi>and now my Crown ſits firm and eaſie on my
Head.</hi> Thus in Vain Raptures would the Queen break out, and boaſt her
Promiſes to be Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical; but ſoon, alas, ſhe found her ſelf
deceived, and all her Glorious Promiſes vaniſh of a ſudden.
<hi>Anaxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander,</hi> and the Princeſs <hi>Artemiſia,</hi> while
<hi>Licogenes,</hi> and<pb n="7" facs="tcp:108547:4"/>his <hi>Pagan</hi> Councellors,
continued only to make ſome ſmall Encroachments, and Breaches on the Laws
of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bion,</hi> ſeemingly deſigning, for no more than a ſmall
To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration of the <hi>Pagan</hi> Religion in <hi>Albion,</hi> kept
them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves within all bounds of Modeſty and Submiſſion, to the King
their Father; only in ſome ſmall Remonſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, they did Declare their
Unwillingneſs to appear Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in the Annulling, or Diſpenſing with
thoſe Laws, made purely for the Security of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi>
Religion, againſt the Practices and Contrivances of the <hi>Pagans;</hi> but
when they plainly ſaw, their Own, and the Kingdoms Intereſt, reſolved to
be made a Sacrifice to the Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Covetouſneſs of a ſmall Party,
that by the known Laws of the Land, were declared the irreconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Enemies
of the <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> they thought it then high time to look about
them, and though they paid all the Reverence imaginable to the King, their
Father; yet they could not reſolve to yield their Rights and Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
and hold precariouſly their Eſtates, at the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion of an
<hi>Anti-Chriſtian</hi> pack'd Councel; beſides, by ſeveral
Remonſtrances and Petitions from the Chief of the Nobility and Gentry, they
had been ſolicited to take them into their Protection, and to endeavour a
Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs of their Grievances, and heavy Oppreſſions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <hi>Anaxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander,</hi> being a Prince of a Vaſt and Generous Spirit, was
eaſily induc'd to condeſcend to their Relief; for, beſides his proper
Intereſt in the Crown of <hi>Albion,</hi> which by the common Principles of
Nature, he was obliged to Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and Defend; he often would revolve on the
Glory of the Action, and how Heroick and God-like it would ſhew, to appear
the Great and Glorious Champion of the Chriſtian Religion, which by a Secret
League, between <hi>Polydorus</hi> King of the <hi>Gauls,</hi> and the King
<hi>Licogenes,</hi> was reſolved to be wholly Extirpated, and Routed out of
<hi>Europe.</hi> Upon theſe Conſiderations, the Prince
<hi>Anaxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander</hi> immediately imparts his Deſires and Reſolutions
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:108547:5"/>to the High and Mighty Lords and States of the
<hi>Low-Lands,</hi> deſireing their Lordſhips Advice and Aſſiſtance
in a Matter of that Importance, to the Security of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as well as
all other <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> which upon due Conſiderations, they with all
Alacrity imaginable Grant: And now the Prince having a Gallant, though ſmall
Fleet, equipp'd with all the ſpeed that could be, makes for the
<hi>Weſt</hi> of <hi>Albion,</hi> and with ſuch prudent Secrecy were all
things managed, that <hi>Lycogenes</hi> had not the leaſt Intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the
World of his Deſigns, till his Fleet was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to Sail.
<hi>Meſſalina</hi> had, that Night the ſatal News ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived, aſſign'd
Count <hi>Davila</hi> to meet her at St. <hi>Jaques,</hi> and the Marchioneſs
<hi>de Tomazo</hi> in the Abſence eſpecially of <hi>Aſpaſia</hi> (who a
while before was gone over to her Husband <hi>Latroon,</hi> Governour of
<hi>Iberia</hi>) being her chief Confident, was order'd to attend. The Count,
who had once or twice been Tardy in the Hour appointed, thought now by early
Diligence to make amends, ſo that by Twi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light he was gotten up into the
Bed-Chamber, being a private Retirement for <hi>Meſſalina,</hi> during the
King's Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence at any Time, or her Indiſpoſition; where ſitting down
near the Bed, he waited with Impatience for the Queen; and in the mean time,
was contemplating on the Happineſs of his Enjoyments; by this time,
Darkneſs had o'er-ſpread the Earth, and the Marchioneſs being to give the
Orders for the Candles of that private Apartment, eſpecially at that
ſeaſon, the Count found himſelf for ſome time very ſolitary, and
without Light, and being about to make to the Door, he heard ſome ſtirring
and breathing on the Bed, when drawing the Curtain ſoftly, he could juſt
perceive by her Cloaths, it was a Lady faſt aſleep; the Count was mightily
amaz'd at firſt, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collecting himſelf, he thought it doubtleſs was
the Queen, who had retired thither before the Hour appointed, and had prevented
even his Dilligence in coming; ſo with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſcruple, throwing himſelf on
the Bed, he claſps<pb n="9" facs="tcp:108547:5"/>the ſuppoſed <hi>Meſſalina</hi>
in his Arms, and having in his firſt Tranſports run with his curious Hand
o'er all the private Receſſes of her Charms, he was juſt preparing to
attack the Fort, mingling with his Kifles, his ſhort Amorous Sighs,
foretelling Tranſports, Extaſies and Dyings; when <hi>Meſſalina</hi>
haſtily comes in with a ſmall Taper in her Hand, and calls:
<hi>Tomazo,</hi> is not my Dear Count yet come, <hi>Tomazo?</hi> The
Marchioneſs at the very Inſtant, whether the Amorous buſtling of the
Count had operated on her waking Fancy, or whether by the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of
ſome pleaſing Dream, ſhe was thereto incited, Cryed paſſionately out,

<q rend="inline">"Make haſte my Dear <hi>Antonio,</hi> make
haſte, the Marqueſs will be here and Ruine us.</q> The Queen who had heard
her ſpeak thoſe laſt Words, by this Time had opened the Curtain, and
there diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered the Count, raiſed on his Knees between <hi>Tomazo</hi>'s
Leggs, and in a poſture which plainly diſcovered the drift of his
Intentions; never were Three Perſons (for by this Time the Marchiones had
wak'd) ſo ſeverally a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhed and confounded; the Queen with Shame
had ſhown her Face glowing Red, and then with Anger ſtraigt grown Pale; the
Count, though in that awkward Poſture, was ſo much confounded, he could not
move himſelf, nor had the Senſe to cover the Marchioneſs, or his own
Nakedneſs; but between Wonder, Anger and Fear, was wholly bereft of even
Senſe or Motion: The Marchioneſs, whoſe Age and Experience had rendered
her familiar with the ſame or the like Adventures, was not ſo much
Aſhamed of being ſeen in that Condition and Poſture, as Apprehenſive of
the Queen's Reſentments, if, as was probable, ſhe ſhould ſuppoſe any
Amour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween her and the Count, her Lover, and whom ſhe had but that Night
appointed, and deſign'd for her own Uſe and Service. In ſuch diſtracted
Thoughts and Manner, did they for a great while ſtand and gaze, and wonder at
one another, without one Word between them, till<pb n="10" facs="tcp:108547:6"/>at laſt
the Queen, whether heightend in her Fancy, with the pleaſing ſight and
intended Action of the <hi>Count,</hi> or upon due conſideration, believing
and judging, by the Words ſhe had heard the <hi>Marchioneſs</hi> utter,
that it was wholly a miſtake on all ſides, burſt out in Laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and
turning her Face a little, told the Count in Drollery, the Weather began to be
Cold, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he would do well to take care and cover his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs
and himſelf. The <hi>Count</hi> with this ſhort repri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand was thoroughly
wak'd out of his Trance, and ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping off the farther ſide of the Bed, was
buſtling a long time to put himſelf in order, while the
<hi>Marchioneſs,</hi> half diſtracted, riſes and pulls the Curtains
cloſe about her; which the Queen ſeeing, She calls out to her:
<hi>What</hi> Tomazo! <hi>You are reſolved then to keep the</hi> Count <hi>to
your Self this Night;</hi> and making to the Bed, She threw the Curtains again
open, and diſcovered <hi>Tomazo</hi> in a freſh Confuſion: By this time
the <hi>Count</hi> had gathered a little more aſſurance, and coming from
behind the Bed, he ſtrait threw himſelf at <hi>Meſſalina</hi>'s Feet,
humbly ask'd her Pardon, and told her, he hop'd ſhe was not inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible
of the fatal miſtake he had like to have fallen in; and conſequently, he
doubted not of her favourable In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation; he was ſorry he had firſt
appeared in ſo indecent a Poſture, and his continuance therein, She could
not but believe the conſequence of his Aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The Queen, who upon
a juſt conſideration of the Circumſtances, was ſufficiently ſatisfied
of his Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, was ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ar from
being angry or diſturb'd, that after two or three fits of Laughter, She threw
her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious Arms about his Neck, and with Ten Thouſand Kiſſes Seal'd
his Pardon: then turning to her dear <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazo,</hi> She would Laugh, and
ſay, Make haſt my Dear <hi>Antonio,</hi> make haſte; O Dear, my Husband
comes! Alas, What ſhall we do? we are ruin'd Dear <hi>Antonio.</hi> Thus did
She Droll on the poor <hi>Marchioneſs,</hi> 'till the <hi>Count</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:108547:6"/>putting her in mind of the time of the Night, they were
retiring to the Cloſet to Converſe, when a Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger from <hi>Alba
Regalis,</hi> comes in haſte, to give an account of an Expreſs,
<hi>Lycogenes</hi> had receiv'd from the <hi>Belgian Lowlands,</hi> giving an
Account of the Preparations and Deſigns of the Prince <hi>Anaximander,</hi>
to come and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs the Grievances of the poor <hi>Chriſtians</hi> of
<hi>Albion:</hi> the Queen (who was no otherwiſe read in the Politicks and
Affairs of State, than as Father <hi>Pedro,</hi> the <hi>Count,</hi> or ſome
other of her Prieſts upon particular occaſions had Inſtructed her) was
not at firſt ſo apprehenſive of the Danger as the <hi>Count,</hi> who was
ſo vehemently ſtart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led at the News, that without any more Complement than
Bowing to the Queen, he deſcends and takes Coach for <hi>Alba Regalis;</hi>
where he was no ſooner Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived, but he found the whole Court Alarm'd; and
<hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cogenes</hi> in Solemn Council was gone to Debate the Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs: The
next Day the News was confirmed by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Expreſs, and then all was in an
Uproar; <hi>Lycogenes</hi> in a great Fright comes to Council, tells them his
ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of <hi>Anaximanders</hi> Deſign, requires their beſt and
ſpeedy Advice, puts them in Mind of all the Brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches he had made in the Laws
for their Sakes; and that now, without ſpeedy Aſſiſtance, he was likely
to be ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in'd, and the <hi>Pagans</hi> Hopes throughout <hi>Albion</hi> to be
ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly loſt. Such dreadful Words as theſe, and coming from a Prince that
had been in every <hi>Panegyrick</hi> cry'd up and applauded for his
Conſtancy of Mind, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible Courage, did ſo amaze and terrifie his
Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors, that they could not in a long time ſet their Hearts on any
ſerious Conſultation; ſome of them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew, then in again; preſently
others that had been abſent, came Poſting to underſtand and enquire into
the Buſineſs; ſome would relate it as terrible as their Fears, and
repreſent the numbers of the Princes Ships and Men double; here you ſhould
ſee a haughty Stiff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necked<pb n="12" facs="tcp:108547:7"/>Prieſt, come humbly fawning to
a Chriſtian Noble, as if confeſſing paſt Miſ-carriages and Crimes, he
wiſh'd for good Conditions: Some would be pack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up their Goods and
Treaſure, their guilty boading Conſciences fore-telling their forc'd Flight
and Ruine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But <hi>Pedro</hi> and <hi>Poliorchetes,</hi> the Chancellour,
who were ſenſible they were likely to ſhare the ſum and ſubſtance
of all unhappy Revolutions, thought it now no longer time to dally, or ſpend
the precious Minutes in uſeleſs idle Fears, but to apply the moſt healing
Medicines, that the preſent bleeding Wound would bear; and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly
perſwade <hi>Lycogenes</hi> to re-call ſeveral Edicts, that by their
Inſtigation and Council had been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulg'd againſt the Intereſt and
Safety of his Chriſtian Subjects: And Father <hi>Pedro</hi> calling a
Convocation of his Inferiour Prieſts, makes them Diſ-robe, and in
diſguiſe to mingle among the Chriſtian Aſſemblies, in the <hi>Forum,
Burſe,</hi> Temples, and other publick Meeting-Places, and there with
Confidence to utter falſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, to leſſen the Strength of
<hi>Anaximander,</hi> to cry up the miſeries of a Civil War, to Extol the
Loyalty of the King's Chriſtian Subjects, to make compariſon between young
<hi>Perkin's</hi> Expedition and this, and thence to conclude poſitively of
the like ſucceſs: The Court party alſo of Renegado Chriſtian Divines,
were order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Preach up the neceſſity of Obedience and Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to
withſtand the Prince in his Attempts, and to brand his Expedition with the
horrible Title of <hi>Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi> Theſe, and many other Arts were
uſed to take off the Edge of <hi>Anaximander</hi>'s Sword; ſometimes they'd
Brand His Royal Perſon with baſe and ignominious Names; other times they
would think to terrifie the Rebels (as they would call all that ſhould
aſſiſt him) with the Exemplary Puniſhments, inflicted by the
Chancellour <hi>Polyorchetes,</hi> in his bloody <hi>Weſtern Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paigne:</hi>
But all would not do, the Chriſtians knew the<pb n="13" facs="tcp:108547:7"/>
               <hi>Pagan</hi> Punick Faith, as well as Inhumane Cruelty, they ſaw
their Laws, their Liberties, and Lives at Stake; and that now was the only time
to aſſert and recover them; the <hi>Pagan</hi> Prieſts had often mock'd
the King out of his moſt Solemn Promiſes, and <hi>Meſſalina</hi> had
endeavoured to entail their Slavery upon them to all Poſterity. Nothing
therefore could ſtagger their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Reſolutions, but like the Adder, they
were Deaf to all their treacherous Charms, and falſe Inſinuations:
Notwithſtanding, <hi>Meſſalina</hi>'s dauntleſs Pride could not 'till
the Princes Landing ſtoop to the apprehenſion of any material Danger;
ſhe'd often chalk out time and place to ſee the fond weak Prince brought
bound to <hi>Troynovant;</hi> She'd Laugh and Jeer at his few puny For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and
would in every Table Talk defeat his whole Battalions; ſometimes She'd call
her Melancholy Lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, whoſe deeper apprehenſions, now had chang'd his
uſual Mirth; ſometimes, I ſay, She'd call him to her, and reproach his
needleſs Fears: <hi>What?</hi> would She ſay, <hi>Can</hi> Davila
<hi>ſuſpect or fear, when</hi> Meſſalina<hi>'s Heart is free? Can thy
ſo much applauded Courage ſtoop to what a poor weak Womans Soul can
ſtand? Stand did I ſay? By all that's good, this Hand ſhall how the Neck
of that poor Spirited Prince, that weak preſumptuous Wretch, that dare Invade
my Husbands loſty Crown: What my Dear</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vila, <hi>canſt thou lament?
Haſt thou a Diadem to looſe, a Throne to be pull'd down, Subjects and
Slaves to be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before thy Face? Theſe may create a Monarchs doubts
and fears: What then ſhould thy Eyes ſwell with needleſs Tears? Remit,
remit, alas, thy uſeleſs apprehenſions! I ſure am the Center of thy
Thoughts: In me thy utmoſt Wiſhes are determined; while then I ſtand
ſecure, What need'ſt thou fear? Chear up, chear up, my dear lov'd</hi>
Count; <hi>let us not loſe our preſent happy Minutes, for vain weak doubts
of future Cares and Sorrows.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:108547:8"/>The <hi>Count</hi> both wondred and rejoyced at
the great Heroick Heart of his beloved Royal Miſtreſs; and tho' he knew,
and was perfectly ſenſible that her words were rather the effect of her
dauntleſs Spirit, than of a ſolid Conſideration; yet he ſaw ſo much
Love expreſs'd in her frequent concernment for him, that he could not but in
common Gratitude and Honour, make her the ſame, or ſuitable returns; he
therefore told her Majeſty, That his apprehenſion of being ſeparated from
her, was with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt, a ſenſible affliction to him; but above all he
deplor'd his great unhappineſs, in not being able to afford more than his own
perſonal aſſiſtance, to repell her own, and their great Prophet's
Enemies; that he cordially wiſh'd the Prince <hi>Anaximander</hi>'s
undertakings might prove as frivilous and ineffectual, as ſhe had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared
them; that his great care of her Majeſty's Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Honour, was the only
Foundation of his Fear; that he did indeed object the worſt to himſelf, but
did not believe he had yet any reaſon to diſpair of the beſt; that he was
ſenſible her ſuper-eminent Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit had render'd her Obnoxious to the
Slanderous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches and envy of the Wicked Chriſtian <hi>Albionites;</hi>
that the King her Husband's Zeal, in a good and pious Cauſe, had incurred the
wicked Malice of his rebellious Subjects; and that if his Affairs (which Heaven
ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid) ſhould happen to fail, it would be the total ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine and
deſtruction of his Life and happineſs, to think ſhe ſhould fall into
the Hands of her Enemies, or be leſſened in her Fortune or high Station;
that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was his humble and hearty requeſt, that ſhe would
ſuffer himſelf, and ſome other ſelect Friends to conſult and lay
before her ſuch meaſures for the ſecurity of her Perſon and Honour, as
ſhould appear to be moſt convenient; that providing againſt the worſt
would be no hindrance of her enjoyment of the beſt; but above all, that ſhe
would give him her reſolution and firm<pb n="15" facs="tcp:108547:8"/>promiſe to let
himſelf accompany and wait on her in all, and every Misfortune that
poſſibly could befal her. <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalina</hi> was raviſh'd with this
ſo zealous and tender de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of her Dear Counts Love, and in a
loving tranſport catching his Hand and Arm, ſhe pull'd him to her on a
Couch whereon ſhe ſate, where with unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Raptures ſhe would
Circle her Snowy Arms and Hands, about his Neck and Waſt; Oh! how ſhe'd
ſuch his Amorous ruddy Lipps and Cheeks, and with her Balmy melting Hand
ſtroak, and preſs, and play with his Manly Neck, and Face, 
<q rend="inline">"Oh! could'ſt thou think Dear Cruel Heart,
ſaid ſhe, that e're my Panting Soul could yield to part with thee, the
Deareſt, bleſt Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of it's joy; Fortune, indeed with rude or
Imparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al hands may catch and graſp my Shaken, Tottering Crown; but ſure
my Heart and Will, are ſtill my own; and being mine, who Dare Pretend to
Stop, or Claim what I reſolve to Share, to Give, to Keep for only Thee.</q>
No, no, my Life, my <hi>Davila,</hi> continued ſhe: 
<q rend="inline">"If Fate or Curſt Inconſtant Fortune have
decreed my Seperation from this Ill-bred <hi>Iſle,</hi> Thou like my better
Genius ſhalt attend me, thou like my happy Star ſhal't lead the Way: where
e're we come we'll be each others Heaven, and in thy Boſome will I place my
Land of Joy, and Reſt.</q> With theſe laſt words they fell together on
the Couch, and tir'd with buſie Love and Rapture, ſoon dropt into a gentle
Slumber. Faithful <hi>Tomaſo,</hi> in the mean time was hovering about the
Out-Guards to prevent ſurprize, and to diver the acceſs of any
ſuſpitious Perſons: She had waited half an hour or little more, when
comes a Meſſenger from King <hi>Lycogenes</hi> to <hi>Meſſalina,</hi>
which brought account, the <hi>Prince</hi> was now at <hi>Sea,</hi> and with a
numerous Fleet was making all the Sail he could for <hi>Albion:</hi> the
<hi>Marchioneſs</hi> receives the Meſſage, and all in Tears repairs with
open Mouth to the Queens Cloſet: the Queen waking abruptly at the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:108547:9"/>Noiſe ſhe made, ſtarts up, and with a ſudden Shriek
alarm's the <hi>Count; Anaximander</hi> comes, Dread Soveraign cries the
<hi>Marchioneſs,</hi> he comes with Speed and Power and Swears to Unravel
all? O Mighty Operations! the Count who had hardly yet recovered himſelf, was
look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about when he had heard the <hi>Marchioneſs</hi> declare he was
come, and putting himſelf on his Guard, ſwore he'd Defend his Royal
Miſtreſs to the laſt; Oh! that his Single Fate, Cries
<hi>Meſalina,</hi> were to be oppos'd to thine: Inſpir'd by Love and my
auſpicious Prayers, how would'ſt thou cruſh his Puny Soul. Soon
ſhould'ſt thou nip theſe daring Chriſtians hopes, and with one happy
blow ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure our <hi>Pagan</hi> Friends and Intereſt for ever. In the mean
time <hi>Lycogenes</hi> in late and early Councels, was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triving how to
ſtop this overflowing Current of the <hi>Princes</hi> deſigns; he had
obſerv'd an unuſual blithneſs in all his <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Nobles
Faces, and was ſenſible that the Prince <hi>Anaximander</hi> could not
preſume to attack the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hionites,</hi> without very good Incouragement
from the Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dee's: however, with all his induſtry he was not able to learn
out who were <hi>Anaximanders</hi> Abettors in this hold deſigne; Father
<hi>Pedro</hi> and others of his <hi>Anti-Chriſtian</hi> Councel were
adviſing him to lay hold on, and ſecure all that he could but in the
leaſt ſuſpect; but this being controverted was found too Violent, and
more than the preſent Circumſtances of affairs could bear; others
ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting the doubtful Loyalty of the great City of <hi>Troynovant,</hi>
'twas thought adviſable to ſecure the <hi>Citadel,</hi> in ſome Peculiar
truſty hands, and thereby to ſcare that Populous and Powerful Place into a
juſt Obedience: this was found good and Feazable, and ſtrait a new
Commander is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain'd, with ſecret orders how to manage things to the beſt
advantage. In the mean time, the Prince <hi>Anaximan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> ſteers away,
and without any lett or hindrance, in a few days arrives ſafe at a convenient
Haven, in the <hi>Weſt</hi> of <hi>Albion;</hi> and now the Thread of Poor
<hi>Lycogenes</hi> his Fate<pb n="17" facs="tcp:108547:9"/>began to crack, now he could
plainly ſee the errours of his Government, and when it was unhappily too
late, might Curſe the baſe deſignes of his pernicious Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors: now
was he forc'd to ſtoop that Glorious Lofty Heart, which dauntleſs
hererofore had braved the mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt force of <hi>Europe.</hi> How was he
chang'd, alas, from that brave Invincible <hi>Lycogenes,</hi> that did through
Clouds of Smoake and Fire, Charge through the <hi>Belgian</hi> Fleet, and with
freſh Lawrels Crown'd, return'd in Triumph to his joyfull Country: now every
little <hi>Weſtern</hi> breeze that heretofore did ſerve to blow and kindle
up his flaming Courage, like ſome cold Peſtilential air damps his
Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving Soul; now Poor, forſaken of himſelf he ſtands, Conſcience
alone of Ills paſt done remains his tireſome gueſt: Attend ye curſed
race of wicked <hi>Jebuſites,</hi> ſee the Prodigious effects of your
Pernicious Councels, ye Cloggs to Crowns, and bane of Power.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Empires to Shake, and <hi>Monarchs</hi> to Dethrone,</l>
               <l>Curſt Race of <hi>Loyala</hi>'s thy Work alone.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Kings,</hi> Crowns, and States o're thrown! no more?
alas;</l>
               <l>Thoſe <hi>Records</hi> fill not half thy Leaves of
<hi>Braſs.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What need thoſe ſtor'd up Coals (ſcarſe worth
<hi>Heavens</hi> while)</l>
               <l>For mighty <hi>Doomsday,</hi> Nature's Funeral Pile:</l>
               <l>Let Thee but looſe for th' <hi>Univerſe</hi> o're
turning,</l>
               <l>Thy Single <hi>Brand</hi> would ſet the <hi>Globe</hi> a
Burning.</l>
            </q>
            <p>The Prince <hi>Anaximander</hi> no ſooner appear'd with his
Fleet, but the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> all about the Country flock'd to the
Shore, and with loud ſhouts and all other demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations of Joy, welcomed
the arrival of their great De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverer: and ſeveral with Boats ſtock'd with
freſh Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion put off and diſpers'd them about the Fleet, for the
refreſhment of the Seamen and Souldiers, and having provided before ſmall
Bridges and other conveniencies for the Landing his Army, and his Carriages, he
found<pb n="18" facs="tcp:108547:10"/>himſelf in a condition within three days to draw up
and muſter his Men, who had by this time heartily recovered the Fatigue of
their Voyage. <hi>Lycogenes</hi> in the mean time, though very much dejected,
had taken care to Levy a Gallant Army, and it was one while thought a very
doubtful thing, to which, to aſcribe the Victory<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Anaxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander</hi>
had not brought with him above Fourteen Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Horſe and Foot, but
thoſe indeed Experienc'd <hi>Vete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rane Bands,</hi> very Compleatly Arm'd;
beſides, <hi>Lycogenes</hi> before the Prince landed, had at leaſt Thirty
Thouſand well appointed Souldiers, ſo that when he began tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughly to
compute his own ſtrength, and his Enemies weakneſs, he thought to take
heart, and reſolv'd for the greater Incouragement of his Men to appear at the
head of them himſelf, and withal ſpeed to give his Enemies Battle, and
hinder their further Progreſs into the Country; but alas, while he was
flatter'd and amus'd with the ſtrength and bravery of his own Army,
<hi>Anaximander</hi> was muſtering and entertaining the Choice Young Men of
all the <hi>Weſtern</hi> Country: for the People conſidering the Cauſe,
and that their Liberties and Lives, were now their only laſt ſtake, they
came flocking in ſo faſt to the Prince, that he had in eight days more
Subſtantial choice Men than he could handſomely make uſe of; beſides,
the Major part of <hi>Lycogenes</hi> his Army, being <hi>Chriſtians,</hi>
they could not but be ſenſible that thoſe Swords that they ſhould draw
againſt their Brethren in the <hi>Weſt,</hi> would at the long run be
employ'd againſt their own Throats and Lives; and therefore, being already
weary of ſubmitting their Free-Born Souls to the Bondage and Tyranny of their
<hi>Pagan</hi> Officers, they aſſociate and take Council to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether how to
free themſelves and their Country, by either, laying down their Arms, or
going over to the Prince <hi>Anaximander,</hi> and now the fatal Period of
<hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cogenes</hi> his Reign drew near, for firſt whole Companies, Troops,
and Regiments of his Army revolt from him, and<pb n="19" facs="tcp:108547:10"/>then his
Friends and Near Relations, touch'd with the ſence of deeper obligations due
to their Country, their Religion and their God: Thus the Trump being turned,
the <hi>Pagans</hi> quickly find their diſadvantage of the Game, and in
Confuſion, like diſtracted Men fling up their Cards, and ſcamper to
ſecure themſelves from payment. <hi>Meſſalina</hi> alſo to her Sorrow
ſees what hitherto ſhe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver would believe; now <hi>Pedro</hi> finds the
fallacy of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions, while <hi>Polyorchetes, Sunderania,</hi> and
others of that wicked Grue curſe their unlucky Stars, and ſeek in every
corner for ſome place of refuge: Poor <hi>Lycogenes</hi> flies in confuſion
from his diſtant Foes, not able to endure even the report of their approach:
He that like another <hi>Xerxes</hi> ſaw himſelf begirt even with a world
of Guards, now flies bereft almoſt of neceſſary Attendance: He no
ſooner arriv'd at his old Pallace of <hi>Alba Regalis,</hi> but in haſt he
calls a Secret and Solemn Council of all his few remaining Friends, and after
ſuch Debates as the time would afford and permit, they reſolve to ſend
propoſals to the Prince, who like a Swelling Tide had now o're ſpread the
Country; and the danger being grown be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond recovery, <hi>Meſſalina,</hi>
at laſt thinks it high time to prepare for her retirement, and with all
ſpeed provide for her Security; the Young Child alſo by the advice of the
Council was to be nicely taken care of, being likely to prove a very good after
Game. The Queen therefore immediately ſends for the <hi>Count</hi> to a
private Conference, who as greedily comes, in hopes to perſwade her to a
ſpeedy Flight: Juſt as he approach'd the Cloſet Door, the Queen all in
tears gets up, and not being able for a while to ſpeak, leans on his Neck,
and after many grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sobs and heavy Sighs, falls Fainting in his Arms: never
was Lover in ſo ſad diſtreſs as was the <hi>Count</hi> at this unhappy
accident; call out he dare not, for fear of any Suſpition or ill
interpretation of his being with the Queen alone; to go and leave her Dying as
he thought, his<pb n="20" facs="tcp:108547:11"/>Soul could ne're agree to; how to
aſſiſt, what remedy to uſe, where to get any thing to apply he knew
not: diſtracted thus he Tore himſelf, and Rav'd, and Curſt his
misfortune, then would he kneel by the Couch where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he had laid her, and
kiſs, and ſigh, and Pray, and call, till at laſt the Queen coming to her
ſelf open'd her dying Eyes, and caſting a Languiſhing look at her Dear
<hi>Count,</hi> who was now in a bitter Agony of Sorrow, and hardly able to
ſupport his oppreſſed Spirits, ſhe rais'd her ſelf a little on the
Couch, and in a Sorrowful manner lifting up her Hands and Eyes, recounts a
freſh the ſum of her Misfortunes: All, all, is loſt, Dear
<hi>Davila,</hi> ſaid ſhe, my Hopes, my Peace, my Joy, my Glories, my All.
And if I have ought left me worth the Thought of Life, it is, that I enjoy thy
Love. That Coronet's my own, though my Crown's loſt. <hi>Meſſalina</hi>
is now driven to the Fatal Period of her Grandure in <hi>Albion,</hi> a ſhock
ſo diſmal, that the Agonies of ſuch a Fall, to ſuch Soaring Ambitition
as <hi>Meſalina</hi>'s, are only to be conceived by thoſe that feel them.
In her fit of Deſparation (for 'twas almoſt come to that) ſhe is Mrs.
however of Reaſon enough ſtill to provide at leaſt againſt the Worſt
of ſhames, and Laſt of Miſeries, her falling into her Enemies Hands, the
<hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> a Danger at that Time much threatned; the united
Murmurs of <hi>Albion</hi> looking up to no other Fountain, and Original of the
Woes and Calamities, of the Pittyed and Deplored <hi>Lycogenes,</hi> then the
Hot Counſels, or rather Inchantments of <hi>Meſſalina,</hi> and her
<hi>Pagan</hi> Abettors. And how heavy the weight of ſuch an
<hi>Inquiſition</hi> would fall, even her Flatterers are but too
ſenſible. Her Flight therefore, being now the laſt Plank ſhe has to lay
hold off to ſcape ſinking, ſhe prepares a ſmall Diminitive Yatcht, and
hires (command ſhe could not, ſo feeble is Soveraignty without Hearts) a
handful of Select Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, all well bribed, and well ſworn, privately, to
waft her ſafe to <hi>Gothland,</hi> the only Sanctuary. (Such
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:108547:11"/>Univerſal Enemies had her Politicks pull'd down) the
World could yield her. Oh Zeal, Zeal, mad Zeal! what Humane Diſtreſles,
Miſeries, Ruines are Thine, and Thy only Creation?—Nay, is there
ſcarce that one Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flagration, that ever ſet whole Nations in a Flame,
that has not been lighted by a Cole from an Altar? Unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate
<hi>Meſſalina,</hi> and deſervedly ſo, the late Royal Part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, to no
leſs than <hi>Neptune</hi>'s Soveraign, the Oceans Lord, and the ſtill
Terror of the World, had not Zeal, Infatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating, Deſtroying, Dethroning Zeal,
blazed out; Poor miſguided, deluded, hard-fated <hi>Lycogenes!</hi> This very
<hi>Meſſalina,</hi> of all thoſe Floating Caſtles, the late attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
Pageants of her Triumph, all thoſe once Impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Famed Walls of
<hi>Albion;</hi> leſt Miſtriſs of no more than a poor Cock-boat!
Inſtead of glittering Flaggs, and flowing Streamers, uſhered by all the
<hi>Tritons</hi> of the <hi>Main,</hi> and as She paſt, Saluted by all the
Ecchoing Thunder from the Shoar; now to Steal away by Night, Skulk like a
Fugitive, obſcured by Shades and Coverts! Yes, Deſtiny and Zeal have ſo
Decreed it! For Sea therefore (ſuch her Equippment, and ſuch the
haſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Cauſe that call'd her) She prepares; and takes with her, her
<hi>Tomaze, Sunderania,</hi> Count <hi>Davila, Sebaſtian,</hi> and
<hi>Pedro,</hi> and ſome others of her Cabinet Friends; the laſt Three only
being a little Transformed, by Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſes of Buff, Scar let and Feather,
metamorphoſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to down-right Militants: For indeed her Eccleſiaſtick
Confidents, eſpecially Father <hi>Pedro,</hi> were grown ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly
Infamous, that they durſt not truſt themſelves in their own Shapes, even
with Sworn Hirelings and Mercenaries; not Gold it ſelf being ſufficient to
pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe Truſt or Safety. The Queen had but very little leſt, to ſave
and carry with her, except her Jewels; for truly in ſpight of all that good
Husbandry, that eminent and ſingular good Quality in <hi>Lycogenes;</hi> yet
what with Stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Armies, and no Taxes (for he neither lov'd or pleaſ'd
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:108547:12"/>Senates enough, for any new Donations from them) and from
the continual daily Dreine, he received from thoſe innumerable Spiritual
Horſe-leeches, that hung upon his Purſe-ſtrings, his Exchequer was but
low. <hi>Meſſalina</hi>'s Jewels therefore, being all the Treaſure ſhe
could ſave; thoſe by Father <hi>Pedro</hi>'s par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Advice, were
committed to the Charge and Cuſtody of an <hi>Italian</hi> Prieſt,
recommended to her by him, as a Heavenly minded man, a Recluſe from the
World, and who as a Perſon under a Vow of Poverty, of a Character and
Profeſſion above any Temptation, was the only man ſhe could beſt
repoſe that Truſt in. Thus Embarqued, with their beſt Sails to their
ſmall Frigat; with a Fair Wind, and Proſperous Gale, they arrive at
<hi>Gothland:</hi> for indeed the juſt Ordaining Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, that had puniſht
her with the loſs of a Crown, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo heavy a Wreck at Land, thought fit
to bound their Indignation there.</p>
            <p>From her Arrival in <hi>Gothland,</hi> the Scene begins a little
to Change: For the <hi>Pagans</hi> there, with no ſmall Homage and Adoration,
reſound her Welcome. The Entertainment ſhe received, as peculiarly
influenc'd by the Commands of <hi>Polydorus,</hi> was every where Splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did and
Magnificent: I dare not call it his Bounty, or Generoſity. For truly, all the
utmoſt Services, Reſpect, Obligations, Protections, or Aſſiſtance;
and indeed, all, and more then <hi>Polydorus</hi> has, or can do for
<hi>Lycogenes,</hi> or <hi>Meſſalina,</hi> ſo near a part of him; are but
poor and faint Returns, to compenſate thoſe Miſeries and Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, in
which his own private Leagues and Cabals, and the too prevailing
<hi>Gallick</hi> Councels and Meaſures in <hi>Albion,</hi> have involved the
ruined <hi>Lycogenes.</hi> With a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Train of Perſons of the Higheſt
Quality, and a Band of Guards, a truly Royal Rerinue, is <hi>Meſſalina</hi>
Conducted to the <hi>Gothick</hi> Court; whilſt <hi>Polydorus</hi> himſelf,
with that ſolemn State and Grandeur, comes to meet her, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:108547:12"/>Congratulate her Arrival; paying her all that Humble and
Profound Reſpect, and Awful Attendance, as if ſhe came not from Quitting,
but to the Poſſeſſing of a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adem: So Pompous was her Entry, that
ſcarce an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique Roman Triumph could exceed it. And indeed ſhe came to
Triumph, the very firſt Sally of her Eye, bringing her back no leſs a
Trophy, than the Heart of <hi>Polydorus.</hi> To give her her Right, even
without Flattery; never was Conqueſt ſo Expeditious: No ſooner was the
very Lightning ſeen, but the Bolt had Executed. So Daz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling were her Charms,
to the ſurpriſed <hi>Polydorus,</hi> that he truly dated his intire
Vaſſallage, from the firſt Moment he ſaw her. His once Adored Dear
Veſtal Divinity, or his Haughtier <hi>Montezania</hi>'s Charms, were nothing
to the Influence of <hi>Meſſalina:</hi> ſo unaccountable is the Archery
of the Blind God: For <hi>Meſſalina</hi> had been no Stranger to
<hi>Polydorus:</hi> when before her Marriage with <hi>Lycogenes,</hi> in her
Travel from her own <hi>Italick</hi> Dutchy, to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of
<hi>Albion,</hi> ſhe took the Court of <hi>Polydorus</hi> in her way; yet,
then her Beauties, though in their Younger bloom, could be beheld without half
the preſent Fatality. For, whether his then Regnant Veſtal Mrs had ſo
fill'd his Soul, as had left no Room for any other Gueſt, or for what
Reaſon elſe; a common Veneration was all the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering he made her then;
when Sighing, Deſiring, Languiſhing, Dying, whole Hecatombs are all too
little Sacrifices now. In fine, ſo Caprieious an Aſcendant had his
preſent Governing Planets, that that very <hi>Polydorus</hi> fated for the
Dethroning of the Unfortunate <hi>Lycogenes;</hi> the ſame
<hi>Matchivilian</hi> Part, before Practiſed againſt his Crown, muſt now
be Acted againſt his Bed. For from this Hour, Friendſhip, Honour,
Hoſpitality, (Obligations not the firſt time diſpenſed withal by
<hi>Polydorus</hi>) and all other ties quite cancell'd; the Poſſeſſion
of <hi>Meſſalina,</hi> though at the price of a Kingdom, is his whole and
ſole Ambition. For <hi>Meſſalina</hi> he Burns, and were her
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:108547:13"/>Virtue a Rock of Ice, (which for ought he knows it may be);
for though indeed he was no Stranger to all other her Intrigues and Affairs,
however in her Curtai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Arcana,</hi> her Amours, he was no Cabinet Counſellour) he reſolves to
melt it down; and that ſo far from a ſcruple at the Undertaking, that he
ſhould account it not only the ſweeteſt, but the moſt glorious of all
his Atchievements. For ſetting all other Conſiderations apart, what
<hi>Polydorus</hi> once but will'd, he could not will unjuſtly; his Ambition
was Commiſſion'd of his Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence's High Chancellour, whilſt to
Deſire was to Deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine; and whatever but once Determined, took the
immediate Stamp of Right and Equity to paſs it into an irrevocable Decretal;
inſomuch, that the very Dethroning of a God, if once thought practicable, to
deſire it was enough to render it juſtifiable.</p>
            <p>As there wanted no Magnificence in all her Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment from her
firſt Landing, even before the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity of the enamour'd
<hi>Polydorus,</hi> you may imagine no exceſſes of the higheſt ſtudied
Gallantry were omitted now. The Adored <hi>Meſſalina</hi> is Lodged in a
Pallace ſo Glorious, as might have fitted the Reception of a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
<hi>Cleopatra</hi> in all her Pride; and which her <hi>Anth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> the then
Competitor for Univerſal Empire, and in all that Love that loſt him the
World for her, could not have furniſh'd out more rich and Splendid: Nor did
the Brightneſs and Richneſs of her Pallace conſiſt only in the
outſide Wealth and Beauty of her Shining Beck, Embroidered Canopys, the
richeſt of Tapiſtries, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binets, Scruitores, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The unſeen
Treaſures, outvy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the glittering
Frontiſpiece: In this Drawer of a Cabinet Fourty, 'tother Fifty, a Third a
Hund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Thouſand Pieces of Gold; a Fourth, Lockets
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Diamonds, a Fifth, Ropes of
Pearl, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And all to mean a Tribute to his Soveraign
<hi>Meſſalina.</hi> And tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<pb n="25" facs="tcp:108547:13"/>now we talk of Pearl and
Diamonds, her own Cargo of Jewels, committed to the true and truſty
<hi>Italian</hi> Prieſt aforeſaid, were under Suſpition of
miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriage; both the Treaſure and the Treaſurer being at preſent
Inviſible: We dare not ſurmize ſo unkindly, that Avarice, or filthy
Worldly Lucre, could pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail upon ſo Sanctify'd a Recluſe from the World,
un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a particular Vow of Poverty; and above all, thought worthy (as we told
you) of the peculiar recommenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Father <hi>Pedro,</hi> could make
<hi>Him</hi> tardy in ſuch a Caſe. But whether, on the more charitable
ſide, by ſome impulſe of Religion he reſerv'd them for Holy &amp; Pious
Uſes; as to preſent them to the Shrine of the <hi>Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rettian</hi> Diana,
to implore from her Coeleſtial Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, her <hi>Albion Majeſties</hi>
Conception of a Duke of <hi>Eborac,</hi> to her Prince of <hi>Cambria;</hi> or
for any other like Dedication to Holy Mother Church, ſo it is, that he was no
ſooner gotten on Shoar, but modeſt good Man, he withdrew, and was never
ſeen after it. And notwithſtanding <hi>Polydorus</hi> publiſh'd an Edict,
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing a very ample Reward to that Perſon that ſhould find him, and
recall the Wanderer: Either his Divine Contemplations, and ſublimer
Meditations, had rapt him above the liſtening to humane and mundane
Proclamations; or elſe his Devout Pilgrimage had carryed him beyond the
hearing of them, ſo that his Recallment is utterly Deſpaired of;
inſomuch, that unleſs her <hi>Albion Majeſty</hi> be content to take out
their Price in <hi>Dirges</hi> for her Soul, 'tis thought for any other
Reſtitution or Payment, ſhe now hopes but little. <hi>Polydorus</hi> now
begins his approach to <hi>Meſſalina,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving an immediate
vigorous Siege, with all the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces he can bring to lye down before her: His
dayly Viſits, Obſervance, and conſtant Attendance, which at firſt
carried onely the Face of common Gallantry,<pb n="26" facs="tcp:108547:14"/>and look'd upon
by all Eyes as no other than the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous Treatment of a Royal Hoſpitality
to Greatneſs in Diſtreſs, and under his Protection; are now both by his
Looks, Behaviour, and Addreſs, ſo Induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly managed, that
<hi>Meſſalina</hi> (unleſs ſhe wanted Eyes) muſt find that in the
Aſſiduous <hi>Polydorus,</hi> there was ſomething more then a kind
Hoſt, <hi>viz.</hi> an Adoring Slave.</p>
            <p>The Queen now fully ſatisfied how great a Vaſſal her Eyes
had won her, begins to conſider the Wiſe Management of ſo Important a
Conqueſt. <hi>Polydorus</hi>'s Addreſs and Perſonage, even abſtracted
from his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Character, and the Luſter of a Crown, were ſuch as
always ſtood fair in the Female Eyes, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd his Heart no
diſ-acceptable Preſent to the very Proudeſt and moſt Diſdainful
Beauty. And our <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalina</hi> who was neither the Coyeſt, or moſt
In-ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of her Sex, already felt a Commiſeration about her, that
told her the Sighs of ſo Royal a Languiſher muſt not go unpittied. Time,
Aſſiduity, and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, ſhe plainly foreſaw, would at laſt
inevitably prevail; and therefore fancying it no leſs then the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute
Ordainment of her Fate, ſhe has no farther Thought then an entire
Reſignation to Immutable Decree. However, though the Stake muſt at laſt
be loſt, yet the Playing her Game out Politickly, and managing her Cards to
her beſt Advantage, are in her own Choice and Power. Yes, that, and that
onely takes up all the buſineſs of her waking, and indeed ſleeping
Thoughts. The Terms and Conditions of a Surrender; What Parly and Capitulations
firſt; what Reſolution and Obſtinacy (for the Victory muſt not be
Cheap) ſhe muſt hold out with, before the White Flag is at laſt to be
hung out. Her Meditations on this ſubject had one Evening led her alone from
all<pb n="27" facs="tcp:108547:14"/>Company into an Inner and Private Walk of the Garden;
When <hi>Polydorus,</hi> whoſe unreſting Soul had led his Body abroad too
with much the ſame Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plations, fortunately meets her. This opportunity
as it gave him the Bleſſing of a more Private Interview, then before he had
met, ſo it inſpired him with the Courage of making a more ample and
particular De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of his Love, then all his hitherto fainter and
diſtant Addreſſes had made. Accordingly throwing himſelf at her Feet,
in the Tendereſt and moſt Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate Expreſſions (the never wanted
Eloquence of Love) he told her how intirely the Soul of <hi>Polydorus</hi> was
ſubjected to the Eyes of <hi>Meſſalina:</hi> Nor did he more heighten the
Progreſs of her Victories, &amp; Power of her Charms, then the Fatality of
them; that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Return of Pity his Death was Inevitable, whilſt his
Peace, Happineſs and Life were abſolutely in her Hands. The Queen, whoſe
part was now to Play, with a ſeeming Amazement, rather than a liſtening
At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, gave him the Liberty of finiſhing his whole Declaration; when as
Wakeing from a Frightful Dream, or Starting from a diſturbing Viſion,
<hi>Good Gods,</hi> ſhe cry'd, <hi>are not your Quivers Empty yet? Have ye
more Shafts reſerved ſtill for the unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate</hi> Meſſalina? <hi>Is
it not enough that your Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting Powers have Raviſht an Empire from me,
and Driven me out an Exile, a Wanderer of the World; but I muſt yet fall
lower; low as the moſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of my Sex, when my Chaſt Ears muſt be
Profan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Rude Sounds of Lawleſs Love; Oh!</hi> Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lydorus,
<hi>Cruel</hi> Polydorus, <hi>has Miſery and Ruine made the fallen</hi>
Meſſalina <hi>ſo little, ſo deſpicably little—No, Glorious
Madam,</hi> (Paſſionately reply'd <hi>Polydorus</hi>) <hi>ſo Great, ſo
Divinely Great, that the Gods have ſingled you out to Weild their Thunder,
whilſt<pb n="28" facs="tcp:108547:15"/>there's not one Bolt of Heaven that Strikes with
Fate but</hi> Meſſalina<hi>'s. Oh! Madam, if ever Compaſſion, Mercy,
Charity, Enter'd the faireſt Temple that ever Lodg'd a God, have Pity on the
Adoring, Kneeling, Dying</hi> Polydorus. <hi>My Life,—alas, my very Soul
depends upon no other Doom but</hi> Meſſalina<hi>'s; for if the Deaf, the
Cruel, the Inexorable</hi> Meſſalina <hi>muſt not, cannot, will not Pity
me, to Die is but half the Tribute my Deſpair muſt pay her: The
Tranſports of a Paſſion like mine are ſuch, that when I loſe all
Hopes of one kind Smile from</hi> Meſſalina, <hi>ſhe leaves me abandoned
to that Wild Torrent of unbounded Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, that leſs then the Abjuring of
Humanity, the Execrating of Providence, and Curſing the very Authour of my
Being, will be the fatal Conſequences of my irreſiſtible Deſperation; a
Deſperation ſo hideous, that when I fall a Victim to her Scorn, will ſhut
me out at once from Earth and Heaven. Meſſalina,</hi> not at all
Diſpleaſed at ſo Paſſionate a Declaration, however to continue the
Maſque of a moſt Rigid and Obdurate Virtue, Reprimands him with all the
Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereſt Reſentments imaginable, deſires him, nay, Conjures him for ever
to Ceaſe a Suit ſo Fruitleſs, and a Thought ſo Impious, a Language that
her un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemiſht never ſhaken Virtue can ſo little hear, that rather then
liv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> within the Air of ſo much
Guilt, her wounded Innocence muſt be forced to Fly a Cruel Court, and ſeek
a Reſuge in ſome kinder and more Hoſpitable Deſart. <hi>Ah! Madam,</hi>
reply'd <hi>Polydorus, Then you have Decreed Mankind muſt be undone! Shall
Empires, Nations, People, have Peace, when I have none! No Madam, 'tis
reſolv'd that</hi> Meſſalina <hi>Hate, Scorn, Loath the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nworthy</hi>
Polydorus. <hi>Yes, his Deſtruction, his Irrevocable Deſtruction's Sealed;
and by the Malice of my Stars, the World ſhall Groan<pb n="29" facs="tcp:108547:15"/>as I
do.</hi> He was once more falling at her Feet, when a Princely Train of the
Nobleſt Quality of the <hi>Gothland</hi> Court appearing in the Garden,
interrupted him. He had ſcarce recovered Reaſon enough to ſuppreſs the
too viſible concern and diſorder, that appeared in his Eyes, much leſs
the Load that lay at his Heart, when one of his Generals Advancing from the
reſt of the Noble Company, threw himſelf at his Feet, telling him, <hi>He
was immediately in Obedience to his Royal Commands, ſetting forward to the
Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Randezvous on the Banks of the Rhine, and came in Duty to Receive his
farther Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Orders. Commiſſion and Orders!</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered
<hi>Polydorus; Why, Burn, Ravage, Ruine, Deſtroy; make Nations waſte, and
King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms Deſolate; ſpare neither Age nor Sex; but above all, where e'er
thou meetſt that loath'd deteſted Thing, that calls it ſelf a</hi>
Chriſtian, <hi>dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thy Fury there, Baniſh all thoughts of Pity or
Remorſe; be Bloody and be Canonized: Remember the Chriſtian Pride is
ſwell'd to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lceration; and 'tis the Glory of our Sword to Lance it. And if
thou meeteſt a Temple, lay the Accurſed Conſecrated Roof in Aſhes; the
God that ſills it is my Enemy; and 'tis but Juſt my Vengeance Battail
Heavens. If thou mak'ſt Treaties or Capitulations, my Orders are, you break
'em all. Betray and Conquer. Heav'n ne'er kept Faith with me, and 'tis but
Reaſon, we the Vicegerents of the Gods ſhould Copy their own everlaſting
Falſehood, and Reign Immortal Infidels like themſelves. You have my Orders;
to your Poſt; Obey and Proſper.</hi> The General upon the Kings Command,
makes his Humble Obeyſance to the King, and Retreats, Ruminating with ſome
little Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize on the ſeverity of his preſent rough Commiſſion;
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:108547:16"/>which however, on what unknown occaſion that had
tranſported him into ſuch Vehemence and Bitterneſs in the expreſſing
himſelf, he nevertheleſs knew to be the true and conſtant Senſe of that
Great Monarch; and all his former Orders, though perhaps ſomething gentler
and ſofter worded, carried in reality the ſame Contents and Mandats; and
accordingly in all Duty prepares to Execute.</p>
            <p>But to return to our <hi>Polydorus,</hi> whoſe Tormenting
Reflections on the Cruelty of <hi>Meſſalina</hi> had, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn him from
all Company to his Cloſet; In all the Agonies of defeated Love, he could not
yet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely yield to Deſpair: Were her Virtue a Rock of Adamant: Nay, were
ſhe poſſibly as Deaf, as Pitileſs, and Remorſeleſs to all his
Bleeding Sighs, as himſelf to a Dying Chriſtians laſt Prayer, he will not
quit the Siege yet. Accordingly not a day, nor ſcarce an hour paſſes that
he does not Viſit, Court, Sue, Plead, and ſpight of all Denials, all her
Pleas of Virtue and Chaſtity, that Mountain Honour ſhall not block his way.
Sometimes he Woes her with the Promis'd Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration of her <hi>Albion,</hi>
the Re-inſtating her in all her former Grandeur; and if the Crown of
<hi>Albion</hi> will not purchaſe a Smile, he'll throw his own in, to make up
the Sum. In ſhort, No Gallantry, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs; no Proteſtations, Vows or
Oaths, though ne'er ſo Extravagant, are wanting to purſue the Coy
Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainful <hi>Meſſalina:</hi> till one Morning in her Walk in the
ſame Garden, his ſucceſaful Rhetorick prevails; or rather
<hi>Meſſalina</hi> thinks ſhe has now held out long enough to yield with
Honour: For after his Repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Proteſtations of the Crowns and Scepters he
would lay at her Feet, and the Vaſſal World he would make her Miſtreſs
of; He told her, <hi>If Meſſalina would but Condeſcend to Crown his Love,
he would pay his<pb n="31" facs="tcp:108547:16"/>Acknowledgment of ſo Divine a
Bleſſing, with no leſs a Sacrifice then a hundred thouſand Chriſtian
Lives.</hi> A hundred thouſand Chriſtian Lives! my Generous
<hi>Polydorus,</hi> replyed <hi>Meſſalina. Such Merit, ſuch
Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent Merit! An Offering of that price enough to Court a Saint, and
Win a Goddeſs.</hi> Such Eloquence is irreſiſtable; nay, the name of
ſuch a Sacrifice ſo pleaſed her, that had the ſtrongeſt Bonds of
<hi>Conſcience</hi> held her, that ſingle Thought had burſt the Feeble
Manacle; and the offering of ſo much Heretick ſtreaming Blood, were ſuch
an Atonement, as would not only expiate but conſecrate the very Sin it
ſelf. So pleaſed and ſo conquer'd, ſhe generouſly tells the
Raviſh'd <hi>Polydorus, That ſhe will expect him at Veſper-time, when
ſhe will ſend all her Retinue to the Moſque to their Devotion, and Attend
his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany in her Cloſet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Polydorus</hi> being now Arrived at the Haven, juſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
entring the Inland of Paradice; the Hour, the Place, the Means and Opportunity
all aſſigned for the Conſummating of his. Happineſs; and what heightned
the Charm, his Divine <hi>Meſſalina</hi> her ſelf the generous Deſigner
of the whole Scene of Felicity; the Plot, the Introduction and Conduct to this
more then happy Meeting, ſo much her own, that poſſibly, our Amorous
Monarch could not conceive more Rapture at the Queens Conceſſion of her
Higheſt Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours themſelves, then at the Endearing management of the
bleſt Minute to beſtow them; even the Portal to Happineſs being
oftentimes with Lovers no leſs Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhing, then the very Temple of Bliſs,
to which it leads.—In ſhort, All things contributing to make him the
Happieſt Prince in the World; whether a Soul, ſo unbounded, as that of
<hi>Polydorus,</hi> whom the Empire of the Univerſe ('tis very well known)
would<pb n="32" facs="tcp:108547:17"/>hardly ſatisfy, had the Tranſports of his
Paſſion, at exalted as thoſe of his Ambition; and was thereby elevated
above the Common Height of an ordinary Lovers Extaſy; let it ſuffice, his
Joy, his unexpreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Joy was ſuch, as burnt in his Face, and glowed in
his very Eyes; and the expected Enjoyment of <hi>Meſſalina</hi> was at that
Moment a Trophy above all the Conqueſts that either his Sword, or his more
Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious GOLD ever won him. But to leave our Royal Lover to all his Furious
Longings, Impatient Expectings, and Reſtleſs Burnings, thoſe Amorous
crowding Attendants, that always make the Leading Cavalcade to the Coronation
of Love: My Reader muſt be intreated to interrupt his Expectation of the
ſucceſs of this Grand Scene of our two Imperial Ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morato's, by the
interpoſing of a little Comical In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigue of <hi>Lactilla,</hi> the
<hi>Cambrian</hi> Princes Nurſe; which, whether by a Frolick of Fortune, for
ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Diverſion of that Fickle Deity, or by meer common chance,
it matters not; caſually intermixing it ſelf in this Sublimer Amour, muſt
make up a part of our Hiſtory.</p>
            <p>It is not unknown to the World what Artful Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs our
<hi>Meſſalina</hi> has all along expreſt for that dear Infant. But
indeed, 'twas the ſubtleſt part ſhe had to Play, and therefore it muſt
be Acted to the Life. In the late Storm that drove her from the loſt Kingdom
of <hi>Albion,</hi> and caſt her on the <hi>Gallick</hi> Shore, however that
darling Infant, with all the Tendereſt Care, was preſerved from the
Univerſal Shipwrack, and not only the honeſt Bric-kill Nurſe that Suckled
it, was carried over with the Queen, and her <hi>Cambrian</hi> Nurſery; but
alſo the very Warming-pan Midwife too, croſt the Hering-pond with her Royal
Mriſtreſs; and as ſome think very timely and prudently, for
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:108547:17"/>fear of that Inquiſition from the Grandees of
<hi>Albi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> had ſhe ventured to have ſtaid behind, that poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly
would have put her to that Teſt her Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances would not well bear;
though truly for a fairer Face to the World, 'twas Induſtriouſly given out,
That her Majeſty was with Child again, and therefore the Midwife's Attendance
being her Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties ſpecial Command, 'twas her Duty to wait on her Royal
Miſtreſs to what part of the World ſoever her Misfortunes ſhould carry
her.</p>
            <argument>
               <p>The Amour of <hi>Meſſalina</hi> with <hi>Polydorus,</hi>
&amp;c. (ſince <hi>Lycogenes</hi> Retiring to <hi>Ibernia,</hi>) ſwelling
ſo big, we are forced to make the Compleating of the Hiſtory the Subject of
a Fourth Part.</p>
            </argument>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
